Brian H. Rutledge

Software Solutions Arlington, MA 617-955-7782 <u>brian@bhrutledge.com</u> <u>http://linkedin.com/in/bhrutledge</u> <u>http://github.com/bhrutledge</u>

I enjoy learning software systems, using them to solve problems, and explaining their concepts and usage. I'm looking for opportunities to do that with a team of people working on solutions that will improve people's lives.

I was an embedded software engineer for three years, then left the industry in 2005 to pursue people-oriented work. I was fortunate to find it at a large bike shop, where I've enjoyed the flow of a variety roles, from selling and fitting bikes to writing and administering software, all focused on connecting our customers with cycling. In my free time, I have expanded my software development skills by building responsive websites back-to-front.

Skills

Adapting, Assimilating, Coding, Communicating, Debugging, Editing, Explaining, Learning, Programming, Researching, Teaching, Training, Troubleshooting

Software Development: Python, SQL, Git, Travis, Linux/Unix, Test-Driven Development

Web Development: Django, Flask, Selenium, HTML, CSS, Markdown, JavaScript, jQuery, Responsive Design, Typography

Experience

Freelance

Full Stack Web Developer

2006-Present

- Built a <u>Flask web application</u> to transform CSV files into searchable and sortable tables, enabling a small retailer to quickly analyze sales reports
- Built my band's website using custom Django applications
- Built my personal website with the Pelican Python framework
- Built a <u>musician's website</u> with the Perch PHP framework
- Developed a PHP framework for quickly building brochure websites
- Built single-page <u>brochure</u> <u>websites</u> with responsive layouts

Belmont Wheelworks Belmont, MA

IT Operations Manager

2007-Present

- Built and managed the <u>business website</u> using the SmartEtailing CMS, and developed a custom front-end with CSS and JavaScript
- Wrote Python scripts to synchronize the store's inventory to the website catalog, resulting in increased customer inquiries and foot traffic
- Wrote SQL queries and Python scripts to generate custom reports of customers and inventory, streamlining tasks such as mailing list generation and barcode management
- Developed a physical count procedure and programmed a handheld data collector to improve inventory accuracy
- Built a Squarespace website for the in-house frame builder
- Configured and managed the MindBody web application to replace a paper binder for appointment booking
- Configured and managed Google Apps for email, calendars, and documents
- Maintained a Google Site for the company intranet, documenting numerous procedures and policies, and enabling easy viewing of schedules and calendars
- Managed a major upgrade of the CounterPoint retail management software
- Established and managed the relationship with an IT consulting firm to ensure timely and competent network management for all locations
- Provided IT vendors with on-site troubleshooting, hardware installation, and new project scopes, resulting in expedited solutions to problems and fewer billable support hours
- Provided staff training and support for all software systems
- Designed web and print forms for collecting customer questions and information

Bicycle Fitter, Buyer, Salesperson

2006-Present

- Installed, replaced, and adjusted bicycle components and instructed clients on pedal technique and posture, resulting in a more comfortable, efficient, and safe experience
- Completed bicycle fitting certification programs from SBCU, SICI, and Retül
- Managed customer relationships by email, phone, and appointment
- Ordered and stocked electronics, saddles, nutrition, and media
- Trained staff and customers on electronics

Darwin's Ltd. Cambridge, MA

Buyer, Sandwich Maker, Barista

2005-2006

- Ordered and stocked raw ingredients and paper goods
- Prepared and served beverages and sandwiches

Applied Innovation Inc.

Dublin, OH

Software Engineer

2001-2005

- Assumed sole development responsibility for a troubled network device, turning it into a major new source of income
- Designed, developed, and documented new features for network devices using 68k Assembly, C, C++, Java, and Python
- Designed and developed a Perl web application for automated regression testing of network devices
- Designed and executed test plans for network devices
- Completed several minor software releases as sole developer
- Completed several major software releases on a small team
- Diagnosed and addressed field issues in conjunction with customer service

The Ohio State University

Columbus, OH

System Operations Center Operator, Lab Consultant

2000-2002

- · Responded to help requests in a Unix and Windows environment
- Designed and developed a graphic FAQ editor in Java
- Provided programming and Unix assistance to students in labs of 50-100 computers

Grader

1999-2000

- Graded papers for an introductory software development course in C++
- Provided guidance for 35-40 students during and outside of class

Education

The Ohio State University

Bachelor of Science, Computer & Information Science

2002

Graduated Cum Laude with Honors in the Liberal Arts, 3.640 GPA